Finding Aid for International Center (University of Michigan) records, 1927-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Director's Files
  - 1962-1965 (James M. Davis Executive Directors)
    - Community Services-Outside Ann Arbor (Box 13)
    - Projects-Orientation (Box 13)
    - Scholarships and Fellowships
      - Committee on Foreign Student Scholarships (Box 13)
      - Free University of Berlin (Box 13)
      - University of Hamburg (Box 13)
      - Guatemala (Box 13)
      - Soviet Exchange Program
        - Correspondence-Donald R. Mason (Box 13)
        - International Committee on Travel Grants (Box 13)
        - General Correspondence 1960-1962, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Other Scholarships (Box 14)
    - Statistics and Questionnaires (Box 14)
    - Student Groups and Clubs
      - Council on International Living (Box 14)
      - International Student Association
        - Cabinet Meeting (Box 14)
        - Committees (Box 14)
        - Election Procedures 1962-1964 (Box 14)
        - Executive Board 1961-1964 (Box 14)
        - Federation of International Students of the State of Michigan 1964 (Box 14)
        - International Student 1962-1964 (Box 14)
        - Miscellaneous Elk- (Box 14)
        - Nationality Clubs 1961-1964 (Box 14)
        - Presidents Council Meetings 1961-1964 (Box 14)
        - World's Fair 1961-1964 (Box 14)
      - Luncheon Program (Box 14)
      - Summer Program 1962-1965 (Box 14)
      - University Activities Center (Box 14)
      - World's Fair (Box 14)
    - Tours (Box 14)
    - Visitors (Box 14)
    - James M. Davis Conferences, Meetings, Consultations
      - Kennedy Letter (Box 14)
      - Staff Meetings (Box 14)
      - Speeches and Consultations (Box 14)
    - Directories 1962-1965 (Box 14)
  - 1965-1971 (Robert B. Klinger Executive Director)
    The fourth sub-series (1965 to 1971) is based on the filing system created by R. B. Klinger. Within this group, topical files of importance concern alumni projects and housing surveys. Other materials in the sub-series include Dr. Klinger's personal papers when he was the Assistant to the Director and Foreign Student Advisor in the Office of Financial Aids (1971-1976).
    - Administration, International Center
      - General (Box 15)
      - Accounts (Box 15)
      - Board of Governors (Box 15)
      - Personnel
        - Emeriti (Box 15)
        - Klinger, R.B.
          - Consultancies (Box 15)
          - Speeches and Articles (Box 15)
          - University International (Box 15)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
          - Personal Papers (Box 15)
      - Madelon Pound House (Box 15)
      - Memorandums 1966 (Box 15)
      - Policy Statements 1961-1965 (Box 15)
      - Publicity, Publications (Box 15)
      - Reports
        - Annual Reports 1964-1970 (Box 15)
        - General (Box 15)
        - Office of the Assistant Vice-President for International Programs (Box 15)
      - Staff Meetings (Box 15)
      - Statistics, Surveys, Directories (Box 15)
      - Visitors (Box 15)
    - Administration, University
      - Director's Meetings (Box 15)
      - Vice President's (Box 15)
      - Professional, Development, and Training Committee (Box 15)
    - Agencies and Bureaus Governmental (Box 15)
    - Agencies and Bureaus Non Government
      - African (Box 15)
      - Latin American (Box 15)
      - NAFSA
        - Central Office (Box 15)
        - Research (Box 15)
      - Near East (Box 15)
      - UN and UNESCO (Box 15)
      - CODFISH (Box 15)
      - Coordinating Committee on Foreign Students (Box 15)
      - Review of Ford Supported International Programs (Box 15)
      - Others (Box 15)
    - Alumni (Box 16)
      - Michigan Alumni Association Clubs Coon (Box 16)
      - Alumni Projects Completed (Box 16)
      - Alumni and Alumnae Association
        - Alumni Council (Box 16)
        - Financial Aids
          - Alumni Contacts (Box 16)
          - Alumni Development (Box 16)
        - Alumni General (Box 16)
        - Alumni Projects
          - Countries
            - Asia (Box 16)
            - South America (Box 16)
          - Grants (Box 16)
          - Illustrious (Box 16)
        - Alumni Scholarships (Box 16)
    - Colleges and Schools-The University of Michigan
      - General (Box 16)
      - Rackham (Box 16)
    - College and Schools-Others (Box 16)
    - Community Services
      - Chamber of Commerce (Box 16)
      - City Council (Box 16)
      - Host Family Program (Box 16)
      - International Neighbors (Box 16)
      - Protestant Foundation (Box 16)
      - Service Club Luncheons (Box 16)
      - Religious Relationships (Box 16)
      - Scouts (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - Student Affairs
      - General (Box 16)
      - Delta Phi Epsilon (Box 16)
      - Clubs
        - City Housing Activities (Box 16)
        - Complaints (Box 16)
        - Cooperative Housing (Box 16)
        - Council on International Living (Box 16)
        - International Center Housing Committee 1966 (Box 16)
        - Married Student Housing (Box 16)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
        - Office of University Housing Staff Meetings 1966-1967 (Box 16)
        - Reports (Box 16)
        - Statistics (Box 16)
      - International Student Association (Box 17)
      - Orientation
        - Handbook for Foreign Student 1970 (Box 17)
        - Student Helper Materials (Box 17)
      - Programs (Box 17)
      - Scholarship Committee (Box 17)
      - Scholarships and Fellowships
        - Foreign Student Fund, before 1971, 1971-1976, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - German Exchange (Box 17)
        - Guatemalan Scholarship (Box 17)
        - University College London (Box 17)
      - Other-Financial Aids
        - Agencies-African (Box 17)
        - Development Ideas (Box 17)
        - Exchange Negotiations (Box 17)
        - Study Abroad 1970-1977 (Box 17)
      - Tours (Box 17)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
- Photographs
  The fourth series contains photographs, both in scrapbooks and individual folders. Photographs are categorized by groups, events, and people. Photographs from the most recent accession are found in both the scrapbook (mostly unidentified) and by loose groupings in folders. It is important to note that there is some crossover between photographs found in the scrapbook and those found in the folders.
  - Activities (Box 17)
  - Events 1946-1947 (Box 17)
  - Foreign Student and Visitors (Box 17)
  - Gale, Esson (featured) (Box 17)
  - Groups (Box 17)
  - Japanese-American Conference, Tokyo, etc. 1953 (Box 17)
  - Korea, Esson M. Gale visit 1957 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Scrapbook (mostly unidentified) (Box 17)
  - Student Groups 1938-1954 (Box 17)
  - Student tours (Box 17)
- Printed Materials
  The Printed Materials series is divided into three sub-series. The first is unit publications that include annual reports, student directories, and manuals. There is a long run of newsletters, under varying titles, dating from 1939 to 1974. They describe in detail the activities of the International Center. The earliest issues also have small articles on alumni of the center. This sub-series also includes statistics on foreign students at the university, including numbers, gender, program of study, and country of origin. In some cases, there is also information regarding foreign faculty members. The second sub-series includes publications from the sub-units of the International Center. These include the Foreign Visitor Office, the Overseas Opportunities Office, and the Volunteers for International Hospitality. Student publications such as The International Student, and the International Students Association Newsletter comprise the third sub-series.
  - Unit Publications
    - Directories (Box 18)
      - Directory of International Programming Personnel, 1965 (Box 18)
      - Personnel Directories 1965 (Box 18)
      - Student Directories 1927-1972, 30 folders (Box 18)
    - Annual Reports 1935-1983, 8 folders (Box 19)
    - Brochures 2002 (Box 19)
    - Calendars 1979-1980 (featuring events sponsored by the center) (Box 19)
    - Reports
      - Archival Report 1970-1972 (Box 19)
      - Community Services to Foreign Students 1966 (Box 19)
      - Foreign Student Tuition Practices at Other Schools 1966 (Box 19)
      - Occasional Papers 1968 (Box 19)
      - Strategic Directions for 1994 and 21st Century (Box 19)
    - Flyers, 1992- (Box 19)
    - International Activity 1985 (Box 19)
    - Manuals
      - Information Handbook for the Foreign Students 1970-1972 (Box 19)
      - Information Handbook for International Student 1958 (Box 19)
      - International Center Manual, 1949-1950 (Box 19)
      - Living in Ann Arbor, 1963, 1978-1979 (Box 19)
    - Newsletters
      - International Center News, 1941-1942, 1956, 1960 (Box 19)
      - News Bulletin, 1939-1950, 10 folders (Box 19)
      - The Newsletter, 1951-1953 (Box 19)
      - The Newsletter, 1962 (Box 19)
      - Compass 1957-1958 (Box 19)
      - International News, 1964 (Box 19)
      - News from the International Center and International Center News, 1965-1966 (Box 19)
      - International Center Newsletter, 1968-1969, 1977-1978 (Box 19)
      - International Center Announcements, 1974 (Box 19)
      - International Center News, 1989 (Box 19)
    - Pamphlets
      - English Language Services 1943 BAC 8059 (Box 19)
      - Information for Prospective Students Abroad, 1955-1963 (Box 19)
      - Information for Prospective Students from Foreign Lands
        - 1949-1954 (Box 19)
      - International Activities at the University of Michigan, 1979-1985 (Box 19)
      - The International Center, 1940-1945 (Box 19)
      - International Center Orientation Program Description, 1993 (Box 19)
      - Miscellaneous (not dated) (Box 19)
      - International Center Services (Box 19)
      - International Neighbors (Box 19)
      - Pre-arrival Information for Incoming Foreign Students, 1973 (Box 19)
      - Program Information, 1938-1941, 1976-1977, 1990-1992 (Box 19)
      - Study Abroad Opportunities for UM Undergraduates (Box 19)
      - Work Study/Travel Abroad, 1978, 1984 (Box 19)
    - Statistics
      - Enrollment of Students from Other Lands, 1947-1957 (Box 19)
      - Enrollment of Non-Citizen Students, 1964-1971, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Foreign Student Statistics, 1983-1992, 1994-1995, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Sub-units
    - Foreign Visitor Program
      - Directory of Foreign Faculty and Staff, 1966-1967 (Box 19)
    - Overseas Opportunities Office
      - Overseas Outlook; Overview of Selected Events 1991-1992 (Box 19)
    - Peace Corps Office (Box 19)
    - Volunteers for International Hospitality 1984-1985 (Box 19)
  - Student Publications
    - The International Student, 1956-1964, 5 folders (Box 19)
    - International Students Association Newsletter, 1971-1972 (Box 19)
- Newspaper Clippings
  Newspaper clippings comprise the fifth series. These clippings range from 1933-1961. The clippings have been kept in their original order and are organized by year and include articles on foreign students and news from the University of Michigan student newspapers, as well as articles related to international news from national newspapers.
  - 1933-1961, 11 folders (Box 20)
- National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (Publications)
  The sixth and final series, National Association of Foreign Student Advisers (Publications), contains NAFSA newsletters published from 1962-2000. Although this collection is extensive it is not comprehensive. The series also includes issues of International Educators magazine from 1999-2000. The National Association of Foreign Student Advisers was renamed the National Association of Foreign Student Affairs in 1964, and again renamed NAFSA: Association of International Educators in 1990.
  - Newsletters 1962-2000, 15 folders (Box 21)
  - International Educator magazine 1999-2000 (Box 21)